{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Skull is not formed on the carbon blocks in the hearth of a blast furnace, when it becomes cold, becaus  of its", "opta": "non-wetting characteristic.", "optb": "high thermal conductivity.", "optc": "high crushing strength.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing temperature of magnesite bricks is about __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "800-1000", "optb": "1000-1200", "optc": "1600-1800", "optd": "2400-2600", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hollow refractory bricks are made by", "opta": "slip casting", "optb": "hand moulding", "optc": "pressing/machine moulding", "optd": "extrusion", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Quartz is", "opta": "stable form of silica upto 870\u00b0C.", "optb": "converted to tridymite on firing between 870 to 1470\u00b0C.", "optc": "transformed to crystoballite on heating above 1470\u00b0C.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An indication of degree of firing in silica brick is its", "opta": "specific gravity", "optb": "fusion point", "optc": "RUL", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Panel test determines the __________ of refractories.", "opta": "fusion point", "optb": "spalling resistance", "optc": "slag penetration resistance", "optd": "refractoriness under load (RUL)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fireclay bricks are not used in the", "opta": "beehive coke oven.", "optb": "by-product coke oven walls.", "optc": "combustion chamber of B.F. stoves.", "optd": "coke oven regenerators.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fusion point of a basic refractory material is", "opta": "reduced by the addition of acid oxides.", "optb": "increased by the addition of acid oxides.", "optc": "not affected by the addition of acid oxides.", "optd": "always less than 1000\u00b0C.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RUL of refractories depends on the", "opta": "chemical composition.", "optb": "physical structure.", "optc": "presence of impurities like iron & alkali.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the stable form of silica between 1470\u00b0C and the melting point 1713\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Cristobalite", "optb": "Tridymite", "optc": "Quartz", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Resistance to slag attack of a refractory", "opta": "depends on the nature of slag & refractory.", "optb": "decreases at higher temperature.", "optc": "decreases, if defective joints & cracks exist in the refractory.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Grog", "opta": "contains both alumina and silica.", "optb": "iscrushed firebrick.", "optc": "is a non-plastic material.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Test piece for determination of RUL of a refractory is heated in a/an", "opta": "oxidising atmosphere", "optb": "reducing atmosphere", "optc": "electric furnace", "optd": "neutral atmosphere", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Magnesite refractories are used for the construction of those furnaces, which are", "opta": "not required to resist the corrosive action of basic slag.", "optb": "not subjected to fluctuation in temperature.", "optc": "used for raising & maintaining high temperature.", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Roof of a basic electric furnace is made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "superduty fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "chromite", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Capacity of a refractory brick to withstand-sudden changes in temperature is denoted by the property called", "opta": "spalling resistance.", "optb": "refractoriness.", "optc": "refractoriness under load (RUL).", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Magnesite bricks are used in those parts of furnaces, which are", "opta": "subjected to temperature fluctuation.", "optb": "required to resist corrosive basic slag.", "optc": "subjected to high load.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is not a basic refractory ?", "opta": "Chrome magnesite", "optb": "Magnesite", "optc": "Dolomite", "optd": "Silicon carbide", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thoria", "opta": "has high fusion temperature (> 3000\u00b0C) but poor resistance to thermal shock.", "optb": "has high resistance to basic slags.", "optc": "which is expensive & radioactive, is used in crucibles for melting high purity metals.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which property of refractories is the most important for top section of the blast furnace?", "opta": "Resistance to abrasion.", "optb": "Resistance to slag peneration.", "optc": "Stability of volume at high temperature.", "optd": "Resistance to corrosion by slag.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractoriness of a typical silica brick corresponds to Segar cone number, '32', which is   equivalent  to   a  temperature  of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1380", "optb": "1520", "optc": "1710", "optd": "1915", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Beryllia (which is used in making crucibles for melting uranium & thorium) is superior to alumina in all respects for high temperature (> 1900\u00b0C ) use, except", "opta": "cost", "optb": "electrical conductivity", "optc": "thermal conductivity", "optd": "fusion point", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An insulating refractory brick should have high porosity and low thermal conductivity. Which of the following is not used for inducing porosity in the insulating refractory bricks during its manufacture ?", "opta": "Cork", "optb": "Saw dust", "optc": "Sand", "optd": "Chemically prepared foam", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing of refractory brick is done to", "opta": "dehydrate the dried refractory.", "optb": "develop stable mineral forms in them.", "optc": "form ceramic bonds necessary for development of high crushing strength in the finished product.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chemically, mullite refractories is", "opta": "3Al2O3.2SiO2", "optb": "Al2O3", "optc": "ZrSO4", "optd": "ThO2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal diffusivity of a refractory brick is high, when its __________ is high.", "opta": "density", "optb": "specific heat", "optc": "thermal conductivity", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "High porosity refractory bricks have", "opta": "poor resistance to the peneration of molten slag, metal & flue gases.", "optb": "poor heat conductivity & low strength.", "optc": "better thermal spalling resistance.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vacuum steel degassing units are lined with", "opta": "silica bricks", "optb": "low duty firebricks", "optc": "high alumina bricks", "optd": "graphite blocks", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pyrometric cone equivalent (PCE) value (Segar cone) of 'superduty refractories' is more than 33 which corresponds to a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1520", "optb": "1630", "optc": "1670", "optd": "1730", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the stable form of silica below 870\u00b0C ?", "opta": "Tridymite", "optb": "Cristobalite", "optc": "Quartz", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one expands on heating ?", "opta": "Silica bricks", "optb": "Fireclay bricks", "optc": "Both (a) & (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractoriness/fusion points of 'superduty' refractories is __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "1520-1630", "optb": "1630-1670", "optc": "> 1730", "optd": "> 2000", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Outer combustion chamber of blast furnace stove is lined with __________ bricks.", "opta": "fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "chrome magnesite", "optd": "zirconia", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Presence of MgO in alumino-silicate refractories __________ its refractoriness.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "lowers", "optc": "does not affect", "optd": "either (a) or (b); depends on its quantity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spalling of silica bricks occurs due to abrupt volume changes, when it is cooled below a temperature of __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "770", "optb": "570", "optc": "270", "optd": "70", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Walls, roofs &  combustion chambers of annealing furnaces are made of __________ bricks.", "opta": "high duty fireclay", "optb": "silica", "optc": "mullite", "optd": "carborundum", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fireclay bricks are used in the", "opta": "coke ovens regenerator.", "optb": "outer lining of L.D. converter.", "optc": "hearth bottom of blast furnace.", "optd": "coke oven walls.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Water content in ground refractory material to be shaped into bricks by hand moulding is about __________ percent.", "opta": "5", "optb": "20", "optc": "40", "optd": "55", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Chromite refractories", "opta": "are bonded with lime and clay.", "optb": "(free from silica) have better thermal fatigue resistance than silica and magnesite refractories.", "optc": "are resistant to basic slag.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Firing temperature is minimum (1250-1400 \u00b0C) for __________ bricks.", "opta": "fireclay", "optb": "direct bonded basic", "optc": "silica", "optd": "magnesite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in the alumina content, the refractoriness of high alumina refractories", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A steel member used in the furnace construction to take the thrust of the brickwork is called", "opta": "buckstay", "optb": "breast wall", "optc": "armouring", "optd": "baffle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "", "opta": "Conversion of quartz to tridymite is associated with 16% volume increase.", "optb": "Conversion of tridymite to crystoballite involves very large expansion in volume.", "optc": "both (a) and (b).", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With increase in the porosity, thermal spalling resistance of fireclay brick", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thoria is an expensive refractory material and is radioactive in nature. Thorium oxide is used in the manufacture of", "opta": "segar cones.", "optb": "muffles for muffle furnaces.", "optc": "insulating bricks.", "optd": "crucibles used for melting of high purity metals.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Maximum alumina content in high alumina refractory can be as high as __________ percent.", "opta": "30", "optb": "50", "optc": "70", "optd": "90", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Refractories are dried in the", "opta": "rotary kilns", "optb": "tunnel kilns", "optc": "sun", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cermets are combination of ceramic and metallic materials due to which they have high strength & resistance to high temperature. Cermets are used in the", "opta": "hearth of the blast furnace.", "optb": "nuclear reactors, missiles & space crafts.", "optc": "insulation of high temperature furnaces.", "optd": "roof of electric furnaces.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hot metal runner in blast furnace are lined with __________ bricks.", "opta": "silica", "optb": "carborundum", "optc": "fireclay", "optd": "magnesite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Spray test determines the __________ of refractories.", "opta": "resistance to slag penetration", "optb": "resistance to CO attack", "optc": "RUL", "optd": "permanent linear change", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}